FABRIZIO RUSSO

Research Postgraduate

@ brizio.russo@gmail.com

% briziorusso.github.io

**** +447784695593

9 144 Lynton Road, SE15RB, London, UK

SUMMARY

Currently studying towards a PhD in Computer Science funded by the UKRI Centre for Doctoral Training in Safe and Trusted Artificial Intelligence (STAI CDT, 4 years program). My background is in Economics and Statistics and, as a consultant, I have led several modelling projects for financial institutions. Passionate about research and innovation, I am studying and developing techniques for explainable knowledge discovery, to the benefit of both academia and industry.

EDUCATION

PhD in Computer Science

Imperial College London

- Supervisor: Prof. Francesca Toni
- Topic: Causality and Argumentation for Explainable AI
- Visiting PhD Student at King's College London

MSc in Applied Statistics (Distinction)

University of London - Birkbeck College

• Dissertation: Macroeconomic Modelling through VAR and VEC

BSc in Economics of Financial Markets and Institutions (1:1)

University of Rome - Tor Vergata

• Dissertation: The Tobin Tax between Theoretical Wherewithal and Practical Feasibility

Funded Exchange Program

University of Madrid - Autonoma

EXPERIENCE

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Imperial College London

• Teaching support for Introduction to Machine Learning course

Freelance Consultant

Imperial College Consultants (ICON)

• Research on outlier identification and forecast for UK commercial properties index

Doctoral Researcher Ernst & Young (in collaboration with STAI CDT)

· Research on back-door poisoning attacks identification for transformer-based language models

Head of Data Science

4most Europe Ltd

Full-time: Feb 2018 - Sep 2020

♀ UK

- Research Lead Replicate Underwriter Behaviour using Machine Learning
- Research Lead Commercial Credit Risk Scoring using Machine Learning
- Research Lead Design, prototype and build an interactive monitoring tool (Tech of the Year National Credit Awards '22)

Full-time: Oct 2020 - Present

Part-time: Oct 2016 - Oct 2018

♀ UK

♀ UK

Full-time: Oct 2009 - Oct 2012

Italy

Full-time: Oct 2011 - Jun 2012

♀ Spain

math Part-time: Oct 2021 & 2022

UK

mar 2022 - Sep 2022 **Q** UK & USA

math Part-time: Jan 2021 - Apr 2021 UK

Managing Consultant

4most Europe Ltd

Full-time: Jul 2016 – Jan 2018

Project Lead - IFRS9 model design and build for three Credit Providers and a Challenger Bank

Credit Risk Consultant

4most Europe Ltd

Full-time: Jul 2015 - Jun 2016

9 UK

UK & Canada

♀ UK

• IAS39 model design and build for UK Credit Provider

• 1A337 model design and balla for off eledit i forde

Full-time: May 2014 - Jun 2015

Credit Risk Analyst

General Electric Capital - UK Home Lending

• Run impairment process for secured and unsecured portfolio

PUBLICATIONS

Conference Proceedings

- Rago, Antonio, Fabrizio Russo, Emanuele Albini, Pietro Baroni, and Francesca Toni (2021). "Forging Argumentative
 Explanations from Causal Models". In: Proceedings of the 5th Workshop on Advances in Argumentation in Artificial Intelligence
 2021 co-located with the 20th International Conference of the Italian Association for Artificial Intelligence (AIXIA 2021).
 Volume 3086. CEUR Workshop Proceedings. CEUR-WS.org. URL: http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3086/paper3.pdf.
- Russo, Fabrizio (2023). "Argumentation for Interactive Causal Discovery". In: Proceedings of the 32nd International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI23).

Journal Articles

• Rago, Antonio, **Fabrizio Russo**, Emanuele Albini, Pietro Baroni, and Francesca Toni (2023). "Explaining Classifiers' Output with Causal Models and Argumentation." In: *IfCoLog Journal of Logics and their Applications*, *Special Issue*: *Advances in Argumentgation in Al* 10.3, pages 162–190. URL: http://www.collegepublications.co.uk/downloads/ifcolog00059.pdf.

Working Papers

• **Russo**, **Fabrizio** and Francesca Toni (2022). *Causal Discovery and Injection for Feed-Forward Neural Networks*. arXiv: 2205.09787. URL: https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2205.09787.

TALKS

Argumentative Causal Discovery

Feb 2023

Invited Speaker

STAI CDT Student Seminar Series, London UK

From Credit Risk to Explainable AI Research

🛗 Jun 2022

Invited Speaker

MSc in Fintech - Politecnico di Milano & UCL, London UK

Causal Injection into Neural Networks

Oral Presentation

♥ XAI in Finance Workshop - 2021 ACM International Conference on AI in Finance - Virtual Event

Risk Scorecards with Machine Learning

Mov 2019

Poster Presentation

♀ Joint Conference of Bank of England & King's College - London, UK

Credit Risk Modelling: Data and Techniques Used in the UK Banking Industry

₩ Oct 2019

Invited Speaker

Q Danmarks Nationalbank Conference 2019 - Copenhagen, DK

SERVICE

- AISTATS '23 (Top-Reviewer Award)
- BSKY at AAMAS '23 (Reviewer)
- AISTATS '22 (Reviewer)
- ICML '22 (Reviewer)

- XAI-FIN at ICAIF '22 (Workshop co-organiser)
- XAI-FIN at ICAIF '21 (Reviewer)
- XAI Seminars Series @ Imperial (Co-organiser)